在东南亚的遥远一隅
In a far corner of South-East Asia,
有一片珊瑚礁三角区
lies the Coral Triangle.
这里有世界上最丰富的珊瑚礁群落
A cluster of the richest coral reefs, in the world.
这座海底城市生机勃勃
Undersea cities crammed full of life.
在拥挤的大都市
As in any crowded metropolis,
有对地盘
there is fierce rivalry for space,
对食物
for food
以及对伴侣的激烈争夺
and for a partner.
但珊瑚礁也是个充满机遇的地方
But the reef is also a place full of opportunity.
一只乌贼
A cuttlefish.
它是捕蟹专家
It specialises in hunting crabs.
但大体型的螃蟹是危险的猎物
But a large crab is a dangerous quarry.
它的蟹钳力量很大
It has powerful claws.
但这只乌贼有独门本领
The cuttlefish, however, has a remarkable talent.
它的皮肤里有数百万色素细胞
Its skin contains millions of pigment cells
可以创造出不断变化的色彩
with which it can create ever-changing colours
和图案
and patterns.
这样的色彩明显迷惑了螃蟹
And that apparently hypnotises the crab.
乌贼可能很聪明
A cuttlefish may be clever,
但鲨鱼更庞大
but a shark is bigger.
它能吞掉乌贼
And it eats cuttlefish.
该走了
Time to disappear.
继续捕猎
Back to the hunt.
不一样的目标 但一样迷惑人的手段
A new target, but the same mesmerising technique.
这些能在拥挤的海底城市中
For those that manage to establish themselves in these bustling
有立足之地的生命
undersea cities,
都能得到丰厚的回报
there can be great rewards.
珊瑚虫在热带海洋温暖 清澈的浅海域
Corals build themselves homes of limestone,
为自己建造石灰岩家园
in the warm, clear, shallow seas of the Tropics.
珊瑚礁覆盖了海床
Their reefs occupy less than one tenth
不到千分之一的地方
of one percent of the ocean floor.
然而 它们却是我们已知的
Yet, they're home to a quarter
四分之一海洋生物的家园
of all known marine species.
珊瑚礁结构复杂
They are complex,
有无穷尽的不同结构
infinitely variant structures,
为它们的居民提供各式各样的住所
providing all kinds of homes for their many residents,
有顶层豪华套房
from penthouse suites,
也有隐蔽的洞穴
to backstreet dens.
在澳大利亚的大堡礁上
Here, on Australia's Great Barrier Reef,
珊瑚石斑鱼以捕猎小鱼为生
a coral grouper lives by hunting for small fish.
但如果你挤不进狭小的裂缝里
But how do you get a meal here,
要怎么吃到自己的美餐呢
when you're too big to squeeze into crevices?
珊瑚石斑鱼也有对手
And the grouper also has a rival,
对方智商极高
one which is highly intelligent,
也捕捉同样的猎物
and seeks the same kind of prey.
一只章鱼
An octopus.
它可以伸进极其狭窄的裂缝
It can reach into really narrow cracks.
即使如此
Even so,
它的猎物也常常会逃脱
its prey often escapes.
如果它们合作呢
What if they could work together?
石斑鱼会变得苍白
The grouper turns pale,
努力吸引章鱼的注意
and tries to attract the octopus's attention.
它在表演倒立
It performs a head stand.
石斑鱼不仅是在向章鱼打暗号
Not only is the grouper signalling to the octopus,
也在说明猎物的藏身之处
it's indicating where the prey is hiding.
章鱼伸入触手
The octopus reaches inside.
鱼受到惊吓
The fish take fright.
直接游进了石斑鱼的嘴里
And swim straight into the grouper's jaws.
有时候 章鱼享受到回报
Sometimes, the octopus gets the reward,
有时候 是石斑鱼
sometimes, the grouper does.
这两种截然不同的生物
Two very different species
知道在珊瑚城里团队合作
have discovered that teamwork can bring success,
可以带来成功
in reef city.
实际上 团队合作是珊瑚礁生活的
Teamwork , in fact, is the very foundation of life
根本基础
on the reef.
珊瑚虫本身也是依靠合作关系生存
The corals themselves also rely on a partnership.
一种更为亲密的关系
But one of a much more intimate kind.
珊瑚虫和海葵一样都属于腔肠动物
Corals are colonies of anemone-like animals,
水螅体
polyps.
有一些水螅和砂粒一样小
Some as small as grains of sand.
在水螅组织里
Living inside the tissues of each polyp,
住着肉眼不可见的微小共生藻类
are minute plant-like cells, invisible to the naked eye.
这些共生藻类
By day flourishing in tropical sunshine,
白天在热带阳光里欣欣向荣
the plant-like cells provide the polyps
提供了水螅高达90%的食物
with up to 90% of their food.
天黑的时候 水螅继续
And when it's dark, the polyps continue to feed
依靠触角来捕捉漂浮的可食用颗粒
by using their tentacles to grab edible particles drifting by.
水螅也会从海水里提取碳酸钙
The polyps also extract calcium carbonate from the sea water,
来搭建自己的石头房子
and use it to build a stony housing for themselves.
珊瑚群落会持续生长数百年
Coral colonies can continue to grow for centuries.
甚至可能一千年
Possibly millennia.
它们能造出人类住宅那么大的结构体
And they can build structures that can reach the size of a house.
最大的海底城市 是大堡礁
The biggest of their cities，is the Great Barrier Reef.
它遍及澳大利亚东北部沿岸1400英里
It runs for over 1400 miles along the coast of North East Australia.
珊瑚礁的内部活动不管在哪里都不会完全停止
Activity in coral reefs, wherever they are, never ceases.
拂晓时分 白天的工作开始了
At dawn, the day shift begins.
伴随着鱼 虾 和其他栖息在珊瑚礁上的生物
Accompanied by a chorus of submarine song,
共同奏响海底之歌
created by fish, shrimps, and other inhabitants of the reef.
这座城市的每位居民都有自己的角色
Every resident in this city, has its role.
食腐动物 像海参
Scavengers, like the sea cucumber,
回收其他生物的排泄物
recycle the waste of others.
这些鹦嘴鱼会咬下大块的珊瑚
These parrot fish, bite off chunks of coral
咬碎它 吸收其中的养分
and crunch it to extract the contents.
其余物质的就被排出去 成为沙粒
And then, excrete the rest as sand.
婆罗洲的绿海龟
Green turtles, here in Borneo,
会定期造访固定的某块珊瑚
pay regular visits to a particular patch of coral.
这个小女孩起得很早 领先了其他海龟
This little female is up early and one step ahead of the others.
海龟要沿着珊瑚礁游很远才能到达这里
Turtles travel long distances along the reef in order to get here.
这就是它们的目的地
This is their destination.
海龟岩
Turtle Rock.
数代来此的海龟在它的顶端磨出了凹槽
Generations of visiting turtles have worn a hollow in its top.
这是鲇鱼
This is home to blennies
还有刺尾鱼的家园
and surgeon fish.
它们会清理海龟身上的藻类 寄生虫和死皮
They clean the visitors picking off any algae, parasites and dead skin,that they can find.
其他顾客也快到了
Other client are close behind.
大家在排队等候
A queue is forming.
一只成年雄性海龟挡住了它们的去路
The big males barge their way in.
较小只的雌性海龟被迫离开
And the smaller female is forced out.
其他海龟还在争执的时候
She takes a quick turn around the block,
她迅速在石块周围绕了一圈
while the others are squabbling.
然后 偷偷溜了回来
And then, she sneaks back in.
清理者饱餐了一顿
So the cleaners get a nutritious meal,
它们的顾客则除去了身上的污垢和寄生虫
and their customers are freed of their parasites and other encumbrances.
如今 在清洗站得到的悉心呵护
And it's now thought, that a spot of pampering at a cleaning station
甚至被认为有减缓压力的作用
may even reduce stress.
中东地区的陆地十分炎热干燥
The lands of the Middle East are so hot and dry,
大部分地表都毫无生机
that much of their surface is almost lifeless.
但是在红海
But here in the Red Sea,
珊瑚礁生机勃勃
Coral Reefs flourish wonderfully.
海岸边的海水
The waters offshore,
有几乎和热带雨林一样丰富的物种
are almost as rich in life as a rainforest.
有的动物来珊瑚礁
And some animals come to the reefs
就是为了休息和放松
simply for rest and relaxation.
宽吻海豚一家
The family of bottlenose dolphins
整晚都在近海捕食
are resting on the reef
正在这里休息
after a night's feeding offshore.
成年海豚和它们的宝宝睡着之后
Whilst the adult and their babies sleep,
这些正值青少年的海豚则出发探索海洋
the adolescents set off to explore...
它们似乎正在做游戏
...and they appear to make up games.
这个游戏可以叫做 接珊瑚
You might call this one,"Catch the coral."
游戏规则不很清楚
The rules aren't entirely clear.
它们捡起折断的珊瑚
They pick up different bits of broken coral,
然后扔下去
and drop them.
有的沉得很快
Some fall fast.
有的慢一些
Others sink more slowly.
有的珊瑚礁沉下去的样子
And some seem to be descending in a way
把大家都逗乐了
that pleases everybody.
只有最成功的海洋居民才能享受玩游戏的奢侈时光
Only the most successful city residents can afford the luxury of playing games.
但是 这些游戏是有价值的
But, such games do that their value.
玩游戏能让年轻的海豚增强身体的协调性和敏捷度
They may help the youngsters develop the coordination and the agility
它们需要这些素质 将来才能在广阔的海域捕食
that they will need when they start hunting in the open sea.
每片珊瑚礁都有明显的边界
Every reef has a sharply defined boundary.
这是海底城市的城墙
Its city walls.
另一面则是海底断层
On the outer side is the drop off.
城墙阻挡海浪侵袭城市
These ramparts protect the city from the ocean waves.
但每天会被潮水淹没两次
But twice a day, the walls are covered by the incoming tide.
在巴哈马群岛 海水的冲击创造了一个奇特的现象
In the Bahamas, the rush of the water creates a truly strange phenomenon.
过去 水手中流传着一个海洋巨怪的传说
Seamen once told tales of a giant sea monster,
它蛰伏在珊瑚礁的深处
lurking here deep inside the reef,
能将水手们拖进无尽的深渊
that would drag sailors to their doom.
今天 我们知道这只不过是潮水
Today, we know it is in fact a whirlpool created by the incoming tide
冲击深处的珊瑚礁所产生的漩涡
rushing over deep coral caves.
这些水流从开阔海面为珊瑚礁带来了
These currents bring in fresh supplies  of microscopic food to the reef
新鲜的微生物补给
from the open ocean.
在马尔代夫 在大潮来临时
And in the Maldives, on the biggest tides,
其中的一片潟湖
one particular coral lagoon
聚集着大量的浮游生物
become so flooded with plankton,
吸引了上百头海洋巨人的到来
that it attracts hundreds of ocean giants.
它们就是蝠鲼
Manta Rays.
翼展可达3米
With three meter wing spans.
宽大的头鳍像是张开的巨口
With their huge sloth like mouths wide open
滤食浮游生物
they filter out the plankton.
蝠鲼们随后创造出一个漩涡
And the mantas create a vortex of their own
来集中它们的食物
that further concentrates their food.
这种行为被称作蝠鲼旋风
This behaviour has been called the manta cyclone.
然后潮水退去
Then the tide changes,
食物来源断了
and the supply of food is cut of.
蝠鲼们便离开了潟湖
The mantas leave the lagoon.
有珊瑚礁庇护的内部生活十分安静祥和
Life on the sheltered side of the reef is tranquil and peaceful.
在这些郊区 任何想要逃离
In these suburbs,any creature wishing to escape
珊瑚城熙攘生活的生物
from the bustling crowds of reef city,
都能找到栖身之所
can find plenty of space.
不过
On the other hand,
这里也无处可藏
there is nowhere to hide.
这让夜晚的珊瑚礁
That, at night,
变得危机四伏
makes it a dangerous place.
夜间的捕食者 就像这只狮子鱼
Nocturnal predators,such as this lion fish,
巡视着珊瑚礁的边缘地带
patrol the reef edge.
猎人变成了猎物
The hunter has become the hunted.
一只博比特虫
A bobbit,
一种巨型肉食性蠕虫
a giant carnivorous worm
有像匕首一样锋利的颚
with jaws as sharp as daggers.
它的祖先能够追溯到四亿年前
It has an ancestry that stretches back more than four hundred million years.
体长一米
It's a meter long.
靠味道追踪猎物
It tastes for scent.
借水流感知动作
And feels for movement.
黎明的光线 让珊瑚礁成为了一个安全的地方
Dawn, and with light,the reef becomes a safer place.
小海鲷返回觅食
Little bream return to foraging.
博比特虫似乎还没吃饱
The bobbit might still be hungry.
但在日光下 形势已经变了
But now in daylight,the odds have shifted.
海鲷鱼看得到博比特虫
The bream can see the bobbit.
它们没有逃走
Instead of retreating,
而是合力把盖在博比特虫上面的沙子吹走
they join together to blow away the sand covering the worm.
夺走它出其不意的优势
So, taking away its advantage of surprise.
暴露了博比特虫的藏身之所
By revealing the bobbit's hiding place,
它们也能够更安全地捕食
they will all be able to feed more safely.
但要真正记住这有只博比特虫
But it pays to remember
需要付出血的代价
there is a bobbit about.
远处的平坦沙地上
Out here, on the sand flats,
有些动物找到了安全的栖息地
there is safe accommodation for some.
鞍背小丑鱼一家找到了绝好的房子
The family of saddleback clownfish have found an excellent home.
地毯海葵触手有剧毒
The tentacles of this carpet anemone can kill.
但是小丑鱼对毒素免疫
But the clownfish are immune to the poison,
它们把剧毒当成了保护伞
so they can shelter from danger.
作为回报 它们使海葵免受食物残渣的困扰
In return, the fish keep the anemone clean of debris.
所有的小丑鱼家庭
As with all clownfish,
总是由一只大雌鱼领导
the family is ruled by a big female.
白色的面部是领导者的象征
Her white face marks her out as the boss.
小型的雄性必须要证明自己的价值
The diminutive male has to prove his worth,
所以他不辞辛劳地工作
so he works tirelessly,
移除残渣 做好所有家务活
removing debris and generally keeping on top of the housework.
他最大的挑战
His greatest challenge
就是为女王找到安全的产卵之所
is to find a safe place where the boss can lay her eggs.
但附近没有固体表面 能让雌鱼在上面产卵
But there's nothing solid here for the female to lay them on.
近处的贝壳或许能够解决问题
A nearby shell could be the solution.
只要他能够将贝壳移到海葵的保护伞之下
If only he can move it to the protection of the anemone.
太重了
Too heavy.
再说 这个贝壳已经有主了
Besides, it has a mind of its own.
寄居蟹
The hermit crab.
但一天之中有两次
But out here, twice a day,
潮水会为海葵做保洁工作
the anemone is swept by tidal currents,
这也带来了新的机遇
and they bring in new opportunities.
旧塑料瓶
An old plastic bottle.
或许 这个可以
Perhaps, this will do.
太轻了
Not heavy enough.
一片椰壳
A coconut shell.
看起来正合适
It looks just right.
但离家太远了
But it's a long way from home.
他无法独力搬运
And he can't move it by himself.
所以他们齐心协力
So the pair now work together.
稍稍调整海葵的触手
A little adjustment to the anemone's tentacles,
给椰壳腾出位置
in order to clear a space for it.
椰壳就固定好了
And the shell is tucked in.
雌鱼产下卵
The female lays.
终于有个安全的育儿房了
A safe nursery at last.
他证明了自己有做她孩子父亲的能力
He has proved himself worthy to father her young.
给这些卵体外授精
And he fertilizes them.
雄鱼会小心翼翼地照料鱼卵
Now he will meticulously tend the eggs,
在十天的孵化期内 保持它们的清洁和健康
keeping them clean and healthy until they hatch in 10 days time.
珊瑚礁生物会竭尽全力让后代活下来
Reef creatures go to great lengths to give their young a head start in life.
世界上最偏远的珊瑚礁
And nowhere more so
莫过于此处了
than on the remotest reefs in the world.
法属波利尼西亚
French Polynesia,
位于南太平洋的中心地带
the very heart of the South Pacific.
这里与世隔绝
Protected by their isolation,
一些珊瑚礁还处于原始状态
some of the reefs here, are still virtually pristine.
这条褐点石斑鱼无惊无险地长大成年了
This marbled grouper has made it in the city and reached adulthood.
是时候繁衍后代了
Now, it's the time to mate.
为了寻找伴侣 他必须前往珊瑚礁最凶险的区域
To find a partner, he must head to the most dangerous part of this reef:
海底断层
The drop off.
黑尾真鲨在此巡游
Patrolled by grey reef sharks,
数量多达上百条
hundreds of them.
它们看似
They seem to be resting,
正在休息
for now.
上千条褐点石斑鱼聚集在海床上
Thousands of other groupers have gathered on the seabed below.
雌鱼腹部充满了大量鱼卵 正待产卵
The females are almost bursting with eggs.
但若想成功交配
But to mate with one,
他必须先击败其他同样在等候的雄鱼
he must first get through the crowd of other waiting males.
其他雄鱼同样也有交配欲望
And they all have the same thing on their minds.
它们争夺靠近雌鱼的绝佳机会
They jostle to get as close as possible to a female.
这条雄鱼似乎已经抢占先机
This male may have secured pole position,
但除非天时地利人和
but the female won't release her eggs for him to fertilize,
否则雌鱼不会产卵让雄鱼授精
until conditions are just right.
鲨鱼群开始逼近
Now the sharks begin to close in,
关键时刻即将到来
sensing that the critical moment is approaching.
潮水开始转向
The tide is beginning to turn.
这或许是产卵的绝佳时机
This could be the moment to spawn.
雌鱼突然冲向海面
Suddenly, the females rush up towards the surface
同时释出成团的鱼卵
releasing their clouds of eggs as they go.
雄鱼在后追逐 同时释放精子
The males pursue them, simultaneously releasing their sperm.
石斑鱼看来准备背水一战了
It's an act the groupers seem prepared to die for.
成败在此一举
It's now or never.
受精的鱼卵
The fertilized eggs,
会被水流冲散
will now be swept away
远离其他饥饿的珊瑚礁生物
from the many hungry mouths of the reef dwellers.
海中如云雾般的上万亿鱼卵
Most of the billions of eggs that cloud the sea,
大多数会被吃掉
will be eaten.
但有少数
But a few,
却极其重要的那些鱼卵
a tiny but crucial minority,
会找到另一处珊瑚礁
will find another reef
在那安家落户
and make it their home.
目前 珊瑚礁正面临新的危机
But today's coral reefs are facing a new threat.
海水在变暖
The seas are warming.
过去的短短数周 海水的温度
A rise in temperature of just one for two degrees
升高了一至二摄氏度
for just a few weeks,
看似不多 但已足以导致珊瑚虫失去身上的共生藻类
can be enough to cause the coral polyps to eject their plant-like cells.
此时 珊瑚会失去美丽的颜色
When that happens, the corals lose both their colour,
以及主要的食物来源
and their main source of food.
如果高温持续
If the high temperatures are sustained,
这样白化的珊瑚
coral, bleached in this way,
会濒临死亡
is likely to die.
近年来 世界上近半数的珊瑚礁
In recent years, it's thought that half the world's coral reefs,
已受到了白化影响
have been affected by bleaching.
其中包括澳大利亚的大堡礁
Including, since 2016,
自2016年起计 约三分之二的浅水珊瑚
around two thirds of the shallow water corals,
出现白化现象
on Australia's Great Barrier Reef.
这些曾经热闹繁华的海底城市
These once crowded submarine cities,
如今只剩
are reduced
苍白的废墟
to bleak ruins.
曾经的居民无家可归
and many of their inhabitants, left homeless.
科学家预测 直至本世纪末
Some scientists predict that by the end of the century,
目前已知的珊瑚礁群
coral reef cities as we know them,
或将成为历史
could be a thing of the past.
这些无价的海洋宝藏还有未来吗
Is there any future for these most precious of ocean treasures?
这取决于海水变暖的速度
Well, that ultimately depends on how fast they heat up,
以及程度
and how warm the seas become.
但由于珊瑚独特的繁殖方式
And there is a glimmer of hope,
还有一线希望
because of the way the corals reproduce themselves.
一年中有一个特别的夜晚
On one special night of the year,
满月会触发奇特的一幕
the full moon triggers an extraordinary event:
珊瑚产卵
The spawning of the coral.
所有的珊瑚礁惊人地同步产卵
With extraordinary synchrony, entire reefs reproduce.
数十亿的受精卵
Billions of fertilized eggs drift away
随着洋流漂散
carried by the ocean currents.
除了珊瑚
And it's not just the corals that spawn,
还有许多珊瑚礁生物在产卵
so do many other residents of the reef.
各种生物的后代
A whole range of young
横扫大洋
are swept through the oceans,
寻觅无人之地 落地生根
ready to settle on a vacant site,
再现这个复杂的生物群落
and bring back into existence the complex community,
珊瑚礁
that is a coral reef.
我们或许不知道未来的海洋还剩什么
We may not know what the future hold for our seas,
但珊瑚礁可以再生
but coral reefs can regenerate.
只要珊瑚礁一息尚存
As long as some reefs survive,
希望便不会破灭
some hope can remain.
法属波利尼西亚
French Polynesia.
这里距离最近的陆地四千多英里
Over 4,000 miles from the nearest major land mass.
这里没有渔获压力
Protected from fishing pressures,
或许是褐点石斑鱼唯一的乐园
it's home to perhaps the last great gathering of marbled groupers.
我们终于到了
We're finally here.
花了好几天的功夫
It's taken quite a few days.
我们不能说出具体地点
We can't actually say where "here" is,
我们答应要保密
because uh, we've been asked not to mention the exact spot,
因为这里是保护区域
because it's a protected area.
摄制团队的拍摄遇到了极大的挑战
The team face a huge filming challenge
因为通常褐点石斑鱼每年只交配一次
as the groupers normally spawn just once a year,
过程持续不到一小时
and it lasts less than an hour.
摄制组的顾问是生物学家 伊冯 萨多维
The team's advisor is biologist, Yvonne Sadovy
她研究鱼类的产卵活动已有30余年
who's been studying fish spawning aggregations for over 30 years.
这里的自然状态与数千年前
Here, it is close to the situation it has been
十分相近
for thousands of years.
这里恐怕是我所知的
It's pretty much the only place on the planet that I'm aware of
地球上唯一一处褐点石斑鱼集中产卵的地方
where these groupers come together in the numbers that we see here.
我非常希望它们会出现
I really hope that they're there
不然我们就得空手而归了
because if they're not, then we've come all this way for nothing.
我们选的时间没错吧 丹尼斯
We've got our timing right, haven't we Denis?
- 确定吗 - 确定
- Confident? - Yeah.
它们不会让你失望的
They're not disappointed.
丹尼斯拍摄褐点石斑鱼的产卵已经15年了
Denis has filmed groupers gathering here for 15 years
他很了解它们的习性
and has got to know their behaviour.
不只有石斑鱼聚集在这里
The grouper aren't the only ones to be gathering.
这还有世界上密度最大的
It's the highest density of grey reef sharks
黑尾真鲨群
anywhere on the planet.
这就是珊瑚礁的原始状态
This is what a pristine reef should look like.
有数不胜数的捕食者
Lots and lots of predators.
既然褐点石斑鱼出现了 那现在的挑战就是
With the groupers here, now the challenge is predicting
预测具体的产卵时间
exactly when they'll spawn.
为了评估拍摄距离 伊冯回顾了当天的视频
To judge if they're close, Yvonne reviews the day's footage.
就我们所见 雄鱼正在向雌鱼求爱
From what we've seen here, the male's courting the female.
如果你能放慢播放速度
When you can slow these things down,
就能看见一些细节
this is when you begin to see some of this detail.
你猜什么时候会产卵 明天吗
If you were a betting woman would you bet on tomorrow?
我猜是明天或者后天
I would say tomorrow or the next day.
我觉得就是这几天了
I mean I think they're pretty close.
只有六名潜水员 摄制组无法进行不间断的水下工作
With only six divers, the team can't stay underwater all the time.
所以根据经验
So, based on experience,
他们决定在满月潮汐更迭之时下水拍摄
they decide to dive on the full moon's changing tides,
想着帮助协调褐点石斑鱼产卵
thought to help coordinate grouper spawning.
但今年 最凶猛的潮汐变化发生在夜晚
But this year, the strongest tidal change is at night.
我们刚准备好第一夜的潜水设备
We're just kitting up for the first night dive.
白天鲨鱼在这片水域徘徊
During the day, we've been seeing sharks around this area, but we don't know
但我们不清楚它们晚上会怎么行动
how they're going to react at night.
你紧张吗
Are you nervous?
礁鲨会在夜晚捕食
Reef sharks hunt at night,
为了以防万一 潜水员穿了防鲨服 戴了头盔
so the divers wear chain-mail suits and helmets as a precaution.
一 二 三 四
One, two, three, four.
潜水员检查设备 检查设备
Divers comms check, comms check.
听得很清楚
Receiving you loud and clear.
褐点石斑鱼尚无产卵迹象 但暗处
No sign of groupers spawning, but in the dark,
鲨鱼蠢蠢欲动
the shark's attitude has changed.
它们在捕食
They're hunting.
鲨鱼利用电感受器来猎食
Using electro-reception to hunt,
他们能调谐到最微弱的电刺激 包括摄影机的
sharks are tuned to even the smallest electro stimulus including the cameras.
洋流正在涌动
With the current building,
现在是与水面失去联系的最坏时机
now is the worst possible time to lose contact with the surface.
我们身处无人之境 也不知道水下的情况
We're in the middle of nowhere. We have no idea what's going on
我们只能听到断断续续的信号
down there. All we can hear is broken communication.
由于褐点石斑鱼没有产卵迹象 他们结束了潜水
With no sign of spawning, they end the dive.
摄制团队决定养精蓄锐
The team decide to save their energy
为下一次潮汐更迭做准备
for the next change of the tide.
长夜初白 他们开始为期待已久的产卵活动
At dawn, they prepare for what they hope will be
做万全准备
the spawning event they've all been waiting for.
坏消息 我们依旧
Bad news, we still are...
但仅仅20分钟 潜水员就浮上水面
But after just 20 minutes, the divers are back on the surface
给摄制组带来了毁灭性的消息
with some devastating news for their crew.
我们错过了
We missed it.
它们可能昨晚产的卵
Maybe they spawned last night.
天哪 我也不知道
I don't... Oh, God, I don't know.
摄制组晚了一步
The team were too late.
我猜我们错过了好几个小时
So my guess would be that we've missed spawning by a few hours.
或许鱼群达到了临界数量
And possibly, it's that they just reached some
或者是临界密度
kind of critical mass or critical density
就提前产卵了
and spawned a little bit early.
第二年 伊冯回到法属波利尼西亚
The following year, Yvonne returns to French Polynesia,
希望能更深入了解褐点石斑鱼
hoping to learn more about the grouper.
今年 劳伦 巴列斯塔和其经验丰富的组员
This year, Laurent Ballesta and his experienced crew,
接受了这项挑战
take on the challenge.
由于潜水员人手充沛 他们有了新的办法
With many more divers, they have a new approach
他们计划让劳伦在水里持续不断地监控
and they plan to have Laurent on watch in the water constantly.
今年 经过数百小时的连续监控
And this year, after hundreds of hours of continual monitoring,
他们终于成功捕捉到这项奇观的关键画面
they have captured the defining moment of this astonishing event -
褐点石斑鱼产卵
the mass spawning of the grouper.
我们有幸亲眼目睹
We have the privilege to be able to watch this process
产卵过程 真的很令人激动
actually occurring. Uh, and that's a real thrill.
它们对动物生物学有重大影响
They're really important for the biology of the animals.
感谢两队专业人士的共同合作
Thanks to a combined team effort from both crews
以及伊冯多年来的研究
and Yvonne's research over many years,
我们终于能向世人诉说 褐点石斑鱼神奇的产卵故事
we could at last, tell the marbled groupers' incredible story.
下一集 我们将去领略开阔海域的广阔无垠
Next time, we head into the vastness of the open ocean.
为了在这片蓝色的荒芜生存下去 有的动物靠速度
To survive in this blue wilderness, some are fast,
有的靠致命的谋略
others use deadly strategies,
有的则依靠家庭成员间的亲密合作
and a few rely on the closeness of their families.
解说：大卫·爱登堡
Translated by
BLINDMAN & BYE & CECILIA
翻译：白虾子 & 小辞 & Cecilia
Supervised by
VERONICA
监制：斑斑
Proofreaded by
CANNAE & WILDER
校对：歪二德 & AlexaJU
Compressed by
DREAM TEAVELER
压制：失梦旅行
Effected by
WILDER FROM SOU
特效：歪二德
石斑鱼一定会出现的
因为它们在满月时前来
这里有成百上千条 成千上万条褐点石斑鱼吧
很难推测具体的数量
还有很多鱼不断加入
它们从潟湖来
到这里的海峡交配
我们得小心黑夜里的深海洋流
尤其是我们还背着沉重的设备 穿了防鲨服
通讯信号良好 看到石斑鱼了 我们正在下潜
我们和水面失去联系了
水下有很多鲨鱼
我感觉今晚游泳的时候有些费劲
我也不知道原因
可能是水下有强逆流
反正我有点费力
晚上石斑鱼看起来没有活动
它们似乎...
一动不动 都藏在珊瑚礁里
鱼都不见了
这样24小时的全天监控
可以让我们有效地观察动物的行为
我热爱摄影是因为
捕捉到珍贵瞬间时的感觉
我从来没有像他们这样
全情投入24小时的连续潜水中
这耗费了我不少精力
珊   瑚   礁
蓝 色 星 球 Ⅱ 幕 后
雷切尔·巴特勒
制片人助理
丹尼斯·拉格兰奇
摄影师
蓝色星球Ⅱ
(学名斑点九棘鲈 俗称蓝星斑)
(每立方毫米的珊瑚组织内有3万个虫黄藻,它们与珊瑚虫互惠共存)
(潟[xì]湖:这里指被珊瑚环礁封闭的具湖泊特征的水域)
(学名鞍斑双锯 与海葵有着明显的伴生关系 是优质的观赏鱼品种)
(小丑鱼会吃掉海葵消化剩下的食物残渣 同时小丑鱼的游动可减少残屑沉淀)
(法属波利尼西亚:又名塔希提,由118个岛屿组成)
(褐点石斑鱼分布于西大西洋区,生活在深水礁石区,可作食用鱼)
(电感受器是鲨鱼头部探测电流的特殊细胞网状系统)
(调谐:使接收设备(如无线电)的频率与所收的信号发生共振的一种频率调节)